Rag is dead. Or at least that's what a
lot of the internet will tell you,
especially on LinkedIn and X. And
personally, I've been doing a lot less
rag content myself. It's something I
used to cover every single week. But the
narrative that rag is dead and it's
being replaced by other things. This is
just simply not true. There is a little
bit where this is happening with some
use cases and we'll cover that, but also
it's a lot more nuanced defining what
exactly rag is. Now, there are some use
cases, especially around coding, where
agents have gotten so powerful with
their search capabilities and context
windows that we simply don't need
traditional rag anymore. But even though
this dominates the internet right now,
especially AI coding assistance, this is
still in the minority out of all agentic
use cases. Rag is still critical for
majority of applications that you build
with generative AI. So, I want to cover
when that is the case and when rag is
dead. Now before we move on, there is a
key distinction that we have to make
together. When people say rag is dead,
they are specifically referring to what
I like to call traditional rag or
semantic search where we have chunks
from our documents and then we embed
those into a vector database. This is
the super classic pipeline. Now rag,
it's short for retrieval augmented
generation. So you can extend the
definition of rag to really any kind of
search an agent can perform because
really rag is just grabbing any kind of
external information pulling it into the
LLM's context window so we can augment
its answer so it has more to go off of.
And so everything that I'll cover in
this video with what coding agents have
been shifting towards it really is rag
just a different kind of rag over our
classic semantic similarity search. This
is what a lot of people are saying is
dead and it really isn't for most use
cases. So the question is rag dead? The
answer for you depends entirely on your
data. How structured is it? So code is a
good example of very structured data.
We'll cover this in a little bit, but
like I said, for a majority of use
cases, we are still dealing with very
unstructured data because we just have a
sea of knowledge that's stored in Google
Drive, SharePoint, our SQL database,
whatever that is, and we just want to
have all that text in our vector
database so we can search through it.
And the important thing here is with our
searching of unstructured data, unlike
something like code, we have ambiguous
natural language. We want to be able to
find synonyms and find text that's
similar based on conceptual meaning.
These are the kinds of things that the
embedding model in the vector database
can help us with. It doesn't matter how
powerful an agent is with searching with
its own tools and with its context
window. When we have massive knowledge
bases of unstructured data, we need some
way to find these synonyms and similar
concepts that can be buried across
thousands or even millions of documents.
That is where traditional rag is still
very much alive. Okay, let me give you
my favorite example here. Let's say that
we want to find all references to Star
Wars spaceships in our knowledge base.
Well, if I simply search Star Wars
spaceships, I do some kind of regular
expression or keyword search like we'll
cover here, there is no way that we're
going to get every reference to the
X-wing or the TIE fighter or the
Millennium Falcon because it is
conceptually similar to our search of
Star Wars spaceships. So there's no
keyword matching there. It's unlikely
the paragraph explicitly says this is a
Star Wars spaceship. Maybe it's
referenced higher in the document, but
probably not in that paragraph that
we're trying to pull in. So we're
relying on the embedding model to
capture that semantic similarity. And so
I know this is just a silly and fun
example, but I'm sure you can think of a
million kinds of searches across your
own documents where you would rely on
something like this. It's only once we
get to exact identifiers and syntax, we
have organization directly through file
paths. This is where we start to get
into very structured data where we don't
need semantic search and we can rely on
these tools built into these agents,
especially coding agents. That's what I
want to cover with you right now. So,
just for a second here, think about with
me the environment in which a coding
agent operates. The first thing is for
the code in your codebase itself,
everything is going to be perfectly
spelled. Now, of course, you could have
a typo and a function name, but that
just means your code is broken. So,
assuming your code is working, that
means that everything is perfectly
spelled and we have those exact
identifiers and syntax. And so, regular
expression searching, keyword searching,
all that is going to work very well.
We're not relying on ambiguous natural
language or having to find things based
on synonyms and conceptual meaning. And
so that is why we don't rely on that
semantic search indexing a codebase and
putting it in a vector database. Also
think about this. We have built-in
organization because we have the file
structure, the architecture of our
codebase. And so the agent can use file
navigation tools to go through different
folders and hone in on where exactly
it's going to be looking for that
answer, like a file you want to edit or
documentation you want it to read. And
then the last thing with coding agents
is they live in the terminal. So they
have access to all these pretty powerful
search tools built right into the
operating system like Rip Grep and Glob.
And so that's what all of these coding
agents are relying on. Now we have some
like cloud code that started with
traditional rag and moved away and then
others that just never implemented any
kind of codebase indexing which by the
way if you don't have to have an index
for a codebase that is a beautiful thing
because this retrieval pipeline is just
another thing we have to maintain with
the coding agent and it is a very
difficult problem to keep the indexed
codebase in sync with the actual changes
you are making to the code because code
changes a lot more frequently than most
unstructured data that we have in a
knowledge base. Most of the time when we
have a vast array of documents, very few
of them are changing even on a daily
basis. And so it's a lot easier to keep
things in sync. So I hope it's clear at
this point that rag or I should say
traditional rag is very much dead for
code, but for most other use cases, it
is very much alive. But don't just take
my word for it. Let's get into what some
of the industry leaders have been saying
with these coding agents as they've been
moving away from rag. The sponsor of
today's video is Scribba, a coding
education platform that works completely
differently from anything else out
there. So instead of just watching the
video and then going to your own editor
to try the concept, you can edit the
instructor's code live and see your
changes in real time. It's like pair
programming with your instructor. So let
me pause the video and show you this
really quick. So we have our rendering
in the top right. I can go to let's say
header and I can change this from chef
claw to chef cole and then I'll run this
and boom take a look at that. We can
play around with the ideas as we are
going through the video. And this is
just the best way to learn how to code
which is very important to do by the way
so you can build the foundation to work
with coding agents and fix the issues
that come up when they hallucinate. And
Scrimbo recently launched their full
stack developer path. Over a hundred
hours of content for both backend and
front end, including frameworks like
Nex.js. And so, like I said, this is
your foundation for building any
software, even using AI coding
assistance. And Scribba has a lot of
free courses to get started. Plus, with
the link in the description, you can get
a 20% discount on their pro
subscription. So, the best example of
this is Claude Code. Boris Churnney,
he's one of the maintainers of Claude
Code. A lot of people take his tweets as
gospel. And so when someone asked why
doesn't Claude use embedding models or
traditional rag, he said early versions
of cloud code actually did use rag with
a local vector database, but they found
pretty quickly that a gentic search
generally works better. A gentic search
is what I was talking about in the Excal
diagram. We're giving our agent these
tools directly in the terminal to
navigate through our file structure and
view our code. And so this is
technically still rag like I was saying,
but there's nothing with a vector
database. And so I'll show you this with
a live example of cloud code. So cloud
code recently implemented this search
tool that hides the underlying bash
calls that are made. So I'm asking it to
not use a search tool and then go
through my codebase to help me
understand how my error responses are
constructed. And so we can see here that
it's using GP. It's using a tool called
said. It's using cat to view the
contents of specific files. There is a
lot of work that's going on here, but
there is no vector database, no
traditional rag, and it gives me a
fantastic overview at the end. And like
I was saying earlier, Claude Code is far
from alone. So Nick Pash is one of the
original creators of Klein put out this
article, why I no longer recommend rag
for autonomous coding agents. And it's
kind of a hot take cuz he goes so far as
to say that the rag narrative is a mind
virus. And what he means by this is
there's this general idea, especially in
2023 and going into 2024, where anytime
you need your agent to search something,
you need traditional rag, semantic
similarity search. And so people would
shove it into any kind of agentic use
case. It'd be completely
overengineering. That's the mind virus
that he's talking about. And so if
you're building a coding agent, think
twice about rag because it's a massive
distraction both for your team and for
the agent itself. And I've seen this
firsthand because I did a lot of work
with Archon last year. Rag for AI
coding, which by the way, this is why
I'm shifting the vision and working on
some things for Archon under the hood.
But I've seen it where the chunks that
you get back from your knowledge base
for your codebase, it just kind of
confuses the LLM more than it helps. And
see, you could even argue that these
tools like RIP GREP are actually more of
a directed and focused search and that's
definitely better when working with a
codebase. And Ader is another coding
agent that's done something very
interesting. What they've done is
they've implemented a tree sitter, which
sounds really fancy, but all that means
is that they're giving an index of the
codebase up front to the coding agent as
a part of its system prompt essentially.
And so this is taking advantage of the
file structure that we have, the
architecture with our code bases. And so
we give the agent an overview
immediately. Here are the files. Here
are the core classes and functions. And
so that way the agent has essentially an
index of the codebase. Not an index in a
vector database, but a simple highle
overview of here are the different files
you might want to hone in on based on
what the user is asking you to do. So
yeah, there are a lot of really cool
strategies that these coding agents are
implementing to avoid traditional rag
and they're sharing that with the world
like we just saw. And so that's what
gives this false narrative that rag is
dead because yes, it is for coding, but
people see that and they don't
understand this key distinction here.
The only reason traditional rag is dead
for AI coding is because of how
structured our code bases are. But yeah,
you can probably think of a million use
cases where you have very unstructured
data and you can't just rely on those
tools that we were seeing earlier.
Customer support, compliance and legal.
I mean you can think of a million use
cases with any kind of internal
knowledge base where we have to rely on
these things and we need this kind of
pipeline for semantic search. Another
thing that I mentioned very briefly
earlier is that there's some overhead to
creating and maintaining the retrieval
pipeline. even a bit of cost for our
chunking and embedding to store in our
vector database. But this is honestly
more of a feature than it is a cost
itself because when we are chunking our
documents, we're splitting them up into
bite-sized pieces of information. So
when we retrieve a chunk, we have just a
little bit of information that ideally
has exactly what our agent needs. And so
it reduced the cost of our agentic
search at scale. This is a really really
rough estimate but it's about a hundred
times cheaper for these really large
knowledge bases when we are performing
rag pulling in smaller chunks instead of
reading entire documents a lot more of
what we'll be doing if we have other
versions of agentic search and so for
smaller knowledge bases sometimes it can
be hard to justify maintaining a
pipeline but when we really start to
scale things our traditional rag
building and maintaining this pipeline
becomes a necessity like right now let's
just go Back to the clawed code example
really quickly. If I were to run all
these GP and said and cat commands,
searching through a massive knowledge
base of unstructured text, this would be
so insanely slow and expensive. Even
just this searching right here was
pretty slow for me, which is good
because we're giving the agent a lot of
flexibility for how it finds the answer
for us. But it's just not realistic to
apply this to a very large knowledge
base. we need more of a directed let's
just pull some chunks here and this
should have the information that we're
looking for which obviously that's a bit
idealistic but there are a lot of rag
strategies that I've covered on my
channel before I want to cover more like
hierarchical rag to actually make rag
really accurate so we can rely on just a
little bit of information we pull
through a few chunks to have what our
agent needs instead of going through
this massive process like we saw with
cloud code and this is really starting
to get at the last thing that I want to
cover with you really quickly and that
is the bridge because like I was saying
there are pros and cons to traditional
rag and other kinds of agentic search.
And so for some use cases it can
actually be dependent on the specific
query over the knowledge base that will
determine which strategy do we want our
agent to go down because what we can do
is we can give our AI agent the ability
to not just figure out what to search
but also how based on the specific task.
And so we can go down either one of
these routes. We give the agent tools to
do both. And so this is still rag,
right? This whole video, everything is
still rag, but it's smarter retrieval
because maybe it figures out like, okay,
I can do a regular expression to find
exactly what the user wants here. So
let's go down the route of anything but
traditional rag, some kind of other
tool. Or maybe it's like, okay, we
definitely need to match to concepts
here. So let's go down the route of
embedding the user query, sending it
into a search in the vector database.
And this, my friends, is what I've been
doing a lot of exploration with
recently. And so certainly interested in
doing more content on this, bridging
between both worlds because giving
ultimate flexibility to AI agents so it
figures out how to do the search. This
is becoming more and more viable as
large language models and the harnesses
around them are getting better and
better. So there you go. That is your
answer to is rag dead. For coding, yes.
For literally everything else,
definitely not. And so if you appreciate
this video and you're looking forward to
more things on rag and AI coding, I
would really appreciate a like and a
subscribe.